

Joseph Iacona, PE

Project Engineer

Years of Experience

Bio

Joseph has more than 33 years of diverse experience working on transportation projects within the greater New York metropolitan area. His experience features the ability to coordinate and address the requirement of multiple parties, including operating departments, elected representatives, and the public. He is extremely familiar with the unique requirements of transit projects, with a strong focus on passenger stations and platforms. Joe's experience includes supporting project leadership with management of on-site construction activities and coordination with designers, owners, and third parties.

WIIFM Statements

Joe is a detail-oriented, effective communicator with years of experience dedicated to rail projects. His career has provided him with the knowledge, confidence, and foresight necessary to successfully deliver the 13 Stations Project.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Halmar International, LLC | Nanuet, NY | 2019 - Present

Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority (WMATA), Potomac Yard New Metrorail Station ∣ Alexandria, VA ∣ \$272M

Project Engineer | 2021 - Present

This design-build project is being built on WMATA's Yellow and Blue Lines between the existing Braddock Road and Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport stations. The 7.5-million-square-foot Potomac Yard mixed-use development is bounded by Richmond Highway (U.S. Route 1) and the George Washington Memorial Parkway. The station will provide walkable access to regional transportation systems for the Potomac Yard area and includes a Metrorail station with two 800 foot long platforms, an entry pavilion, a 200 foot pedestrian/bicycle bridge spanning the CSX and WMATA rail tracks, a 200 foot pedestrian bridge to the North Pavilion, a 350 foot pedestrian bridge to the possible future Glebe Pavilion, a landscaped approach to the Potomac Greens neighborhood, power upgrades to six other stations, a new AC switchgear room, and re-alignment of the Metrorail tracks through the new station. The station, pavilions, platform, and bridge piers are constructed on a combination of consolidated soil and piles. The inside of the station and pavilion provide access to the mezzanine and pedestrian bridge via stairs, elevators, and escalators — making it a fully ADA accessible facility. The pedestrian bridges feature an open-air design, using a steel truss design, cast-in-place walkway, steel mesh enclosure, and the zinc-coated, curved standing seam metal roof that adds to the aesthetics of the facility.

As Project Engineer, Joe is responsible for coordinating the construction work on site, including the work of specialty subcontractors. Additionally, he is responsible for processing change orders, tracking construction work, submittals, RFIs, As-Built drawings, and development of a Safe Work Plan.

MTA-Long Island Rail Road (LIRR), Third Track Expansion | Floral Park Queens to Hicksville Long Island, NY | \$1.813B

Project Engineer for Stations | 2019 – 2021

10-mile track expansion design-build project including construction of six new railroad bridges and five New York State Department of Transportation (NYSDOT) roadway bridges, the replacement of five existing railroad bridges, and widening of three existing railroad bridges to accommodate the new mainline third track. The project also includes replacement and/or modifications to seven passenger rail stations, including platforms, station access,



passenger shelters, ADA enhancements; utility relocations including electric, signal, communications, gas, water, sewer, and storm sewer systems; and five new parking facilities.

Joe assisted with design development and coordination between the JV, lead designer, and LIRR; procurement of materials and associated logistics; and oversight of subcontractors.

Tutor Perini Corporation | Project Engineer | 2013 – 2019 MTA-LIRR, Grand Central Terminal Station Caverns Passenger Train Station | New York, NY | \$663M

Project Engineer | 2016 – 2018

Underground train station terminal to open commuter train passenger movement from Long Island into midtown Manhattan. Responsible for the installation of architectural finishes and vertical circulation elements, including stone wall panels and tiles, flooring, granite pavers and stair treads, platform edge finishes, rubbing boards, granite tactile tile warning strip, glass mosaic tile passageway wall finishes, door assemblies and hardware, floor hatches and handrails and guardrails. This included managing subcontracted architectural work: truncated-dome tactile warning strip stone pavers along eight train platform edges (8,000 LF); polished stone flooring throughout four train platforms and two mezzanine passenger movement areas (250,000 sf); vertical circulation elements of 16 passenger escalators and six elevators; tile work of mezzanine level passenger areas; granite stone tread work of twenty stairwells; and managed material procurement of door assemblies and associated hardware, floor hatches, gratings, handrails and guardrails.

LIRR/Related Companies, Hudson Yards Overbuild Platform | New York, NY | \$564M Field Engineer | 2013 – 2016

Responsible for the installation of drilled caisson foundations within existing railroad storage yard for support of structural steel columns, beams trusses plate girders spanning thirty railroad tracks for purpose of concrete deck overbuild platform; required relocation of underground utilities to accommodate drilling locations; coordination with LIRR Track Outages and Hi-Rail equipment.

John Civetta & Sons, Inc. | Project Engineer | 2010 – 2012

MTA-New York City Transit (NYCT), Transit Seven Station Broadway Line Rehabilitation Elevated Subway No. 1 Line | the Bronx, NY | \$46M

Project Engineer/Site Safety Engineer | 2010 – 2012

Renovation of train platform slabs and edges, railings, stairways, canopy, control house standing-seam metal roofing, and drainage systems at seven stations (7th Avenue 1 Line Dyckman Street; 207th Street; 215th Street; 225th Street; and 230th 240th Van Cortland Stations). Project also included existing steel column base repairs, timber purlin and beam replacement of canopy, landmarked restoration of timber columns, braces, and purlins.

Judlau Contracting, Inc. | Project Engineer | 2004 – 2010 MTA-NYCT, Rehabilitation Myrtle-Wyckoff Stations | Queens, NY | \$48M

Project Engineer

Project description and responsibilities...

MTA-NYCT, Rehabilitation 59th St. Columbus Circle Subway Station West 59th Street/ 7th Ave. | New York, NY | \$71M

Project Manager

Reconstruct eight pedestrian platforms for boarding subways 1, 2, 3, A, B, C, D lines, stairways, lighting, plumbing, fire protection water, floor and wall tile finishes, doors, facilities, mechanical rooms HVAC systems, glass storefront/retail area collection booths, turnstiles, gates artwork installation and landmark restorative work.

D&S/Zaffuto Construction, JV | Project Manager | 2001 – 2004

New York City Housing Authority, Rehab Edgemere-Arverne Houses | Rockaway | \$48M

Project Manager



MTA-NYCT, Rehab Marlboro Houses | Brooklyn, NY | \$16M

Project Manager

Project description and responsibilities...

The DiSalvo Ericson Engineering Group | 2000 – 2001 Design Engineer

Responsibilities...

NYC SCA – Office to Inspector General | 1998 – 2000 Investigative Engineer

Responsibilities...

Pall Corporation | 1989 – 1998

Senior Design Engineer

Responsibilities...

EDUCATION

M.S. in Civil Engineering, Manhattan College, 1998

B.S. in Mechanical Engineering, University of Rochester, 1989

REGISTRATIONS / CERTIFICATIONS

NY State Professional Engineer, License No. 076509

WORK HISTORY

Halmar (Project Engineer): 2019 – Present

Tutor Perini Corporation (Project Engineer): 2013 – 2019 John Civetta & Sons, Inc. (Field Engineer): 2010 – 2012

Judlau Contracting, Inc. (Project Manager/Project Engineer): 2004 – 2010

D&S/Zaffuto Construction, JV (Project Manager): 2001 - 2004

The DiSalvo Ericson Engineering Group (Design Engineer): 2000 – 2001 NYC SCA – Office to Inspector General (Investigative Engineer): 1998 – 2000

Pall Corporation (Senior Design Engineer): 1989 – 1998

REFERENCES

Fred Robertson, PE, DBIA, WMATA Sr. Capital Program Manager, frobertson@wmata.com, (703)667.2628 Mark Roche, MTA Sr. Director of Alternative Project Delivery, mroche@mtahq.org, (212)878.7459